A Guide to the Warren County (Va.) County Court Records, 1836-1903
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Warren County (Va.) County Court Records, 1836-1903
The Library of Virginia
1096407-1096591 circa
26 v.
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in a shipment of court papers from Warren County.
Historical Information
Warren County was named for Joseph Warren, the revolutionary patriot who sent Paul Revere and William Dawes on their famous rides and who was killed at the Battle of Bunker Hill. The county was formed from Frederick and Shenandoah counties in 1836.
A Docket is a brief record of proceedings in a court of justice. It usually gives the style of the suit and the date the court first dealt with it. Sometime it gives the date the suit was removed from the docket.
An issue is the act of issuing or promulgating; e.g. to issue an order or writ. An issue docket is the record of issuance, showing parties' names, actions, and remarks.
An execution is a court order directing a sheriff or other officer to enforce a judgment, usually by seizing and selling the judgment debtor's property. An Execution Books lists executions sued out or pending in the sheriff's office. It shows notices of process, names of all parties, amount of judgment, date of execution, return date and sheriff's return.
A Writ is a written judicial order to perform a specified act, or giving authority to have it done. A written court order of a judicial process, directing that a sheriff or other judicial officer do what is commanded by the writ; or giving authority and commission to have it done. The Writ Docket is a book that have brief entries concerning writs that were enforced.
Fee Books are volumes showing the date of a duty performed by the clerk, the name of the person paying the fees, and the amount. It includes the fees charged attorneys, cash accounts, and the clerk's fees in common law and chancery cause.
A Memorandum Book is used for notations of entries to be made in other books.
Judgments are civil cases in which justice was administered on the strictly formulated rules of common law. The majority of cases in this record series relate to matters of debt.
Scope and Content
Warren County (Va.) County Court Records, 1836-1903 contains Chancery Issue Docket, Common Law Issue Dockets, Memorandum Books, Writ Docket, Process Books A and B, Common Law Rules Books A and B, Record of Judgments, Fee Books, Executions, Volumes A-D, Index A to Minute Books, Chancery Writ Docket, and Witness Attendance Books.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Warren County court records can be found on microfilm at the Library of Virginia. Consult "A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm"
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Warren County (Va.) Circuit Court
Subjects:
Court Records--Virginia--Warren County
Geographical Names:
Warren County (Va.)--History
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records--Virginia--Warren County; Judicial records--Virginia--Warren County; Public records--Virginia--Warren County
Contents List
- Chancery Issue Docket, 1871-1873
  This volume contains a record of Issues made by the Chancery Court.
- Common Law Issue Dockets, 1850-1873 (bulk 1850-1862)
  Barcode Number 1096416 contains Common Law Issue Dockets, 1850-1862. Barcode Number 1096415 contains Common Law Issue Dockets, 1871-1873.
- Memorandum Books, 1836-1865 (bulk 1844-1865)
  Barcode Number 1096439 contains Memorandum Book, 1836-1838. Barcode Number 1096420 contains Memorandum Book, 1839-1842. Barcode Number 1096419 contains Memorandum Book, 1844-1850. Barcode Number 1096418 contains Memorandum Book, 1851-1865.
- Writ Docket, 1836-1849
  The book has brief entries concerning writs that were enforced.
- Process Book A, 1836-1861
  This book shows how the court exercised jurisdiction over a person or a specific property.
- Process Book B, 1860-1894
- ,Common Law Rule Book A 1836-1870
  Rules was a session of the Court. Some judgments were solved in Rules and others were sent to be heard in a Court.
- Common Law Rule Book B, 1871-1873
- Records of Judgments 1843-1887 (bulk 1843-1877)
  Barcode Number 1096472 contains Record of Judgments, 1843-1877. Barcode Number 1096473 contains Record of Judgments, 1880-1887.
- Fee Books, 1836-1868.
  Barcode Number 1096477 contains Fee Book, 1836-1847. Barcode Number 1096508 contains Fee Book, 1847-1856. Barcode Number 1096507 contains Fee Book, 1856-1859. Barcode Number 1096510 contains Fee Book, 1860-1868.
- Executions, Volumes A-D, 1836-1903
  Barcode Number 1096480 contains Executions, Volume A, 1836-1845. Barcode Number 1096483 contains Executions, Volume B, 1845-1867. Barcode Number 1096481 contains Executions, Volume C, 1867-1875. Barcode Number 1096482 contains Executions, Volume D, 1875-1903.
- Index A to Minute Books, 1836-1872
  Minute books contain brief entries of the business heard at Court.
- Witness Attendance Books, 1836-1888
  Barcode Number 1096591 contains Witness Attendance Book, 1836-1871. Barcode Number 1096492 contains Witness Attendance Book, 1871-1888.
- Chancery Writ Docket, 1850-1879
  This book has brief entries concerning writs ordered by the Chancery Court that were enforced.